{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The northern half of this peninsula was controlled in the 600s by an Exarchate [[EKS-ar-kate]] based in Ravenna. Hannibal Barca crossed the Alps with a mercenary army to raid this peninsula which hosts several microstates, including San Marino and Vatican City. For ten points, name this peninsula, the former home of the Etruscan civilization and the heart of the Roman Empire. ANSWER:ItalianPeninsula (acceptItalicPeninsula;acceptApenninePeninsula before \"Apennine\" is mentioned; acceptItaly) (2) This leader obtained a doctorate in quantum chemistry in 1986 prior to entering politics. This politician played a central role in negotiating the Treaty of Lisbon and was a main figure behind the stimulus plan to help shelter the European Union from the Great Recession. The leader of the Christian Democratic Union from 2000 to 2018, this politician was elected to her highestpositionin2005.Fortenpoints,namethisfirstfemalechancellor of Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "AngelaMerkelor Angela DorotheaMerkel",
        "Angela DorotheaKasner"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Friedrich Miescher [[MEE-shuh]] first identified this molecule in 1869, calling it nuclein. Helicases create a \"fork\" during the replication of this molecule, whose structure was identified thanks to Rosalind Franklin's Photo 51. For ten points, name this molecule that is often sequenced, best identifiedbyitsdouble-helixstructuredocumentedbyWatson and Crick. ANSWER:DNA(acceptDeoxyribonucleic acid) (4) This man ordered the Hungnam Evacuation following his failure to predict an invasion by the People's Volunteer Army. This man's failure to abandon the strategically insignificant site of Peleliu [[peh-LEH-loo]] resulted in devastating losses for U.S. marines. This man's support of the use of nuclear weapons in the Korean War led to his sacking by Harry S. Truman. For ten points, name this Supreme Allied commander in the Pacific Theater.",
      "answer": "DouglasMacArthur 2021-22 C Set History"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler called Foreign Minister Nikita Panin a \"personal encyclopedia,\" though Panin fell out of favor byadvocatingfortheNorthernAlliancewithPrussia.Toconvincethis empress that the typical serf fares well, herloverandadvisorGrigoryPotemkinsupposedly showed her retinue false villages in Crimea. Upon conversion to the Russian Orthodox church, the name Yekaterina wasgivento,fortenpoints,whichRussianempressofthe18th century? ANSWER:Catherinethe Great (acceptCatherineII;acceptYekaterinaII before mentioned) (6) The \"Plan of the Three Guarantees\" in this nation's city of Iguala established a short-lived Constitutional Monarchythere.Theransackingofaforeignchef'sshopledtothe First French Intervention in this nation during the Pastry War. This nation's war of independence began after the Grito de Dolores by Don Miguel Hidalgo. Much of New Spain was made up of, for ten points, what North American nation to the south of the United States?",
      "answer": [
        "United States ofMexicoor Estados UnidosMexicanos",
        "acceptEUM",
        "First MexicanEmpire",
        "FirstMexicanRepublic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This one-time Minister of France refused to condemn the Reign of Terror saying it would \"Undermine the cause of republicanism in America.\" With James Madison, this man sponsored and wrote the National Gazette to raise money for his agrarian party. For ten points, name this Secretary of State in the first presidential cabinet, the rival of Alexander Hamilton and principal author of the Declaration of Independence.",
      "answer": "ThomasJefferson"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ibn Battuta claimed that this structure's purpose was to keep out demonic beasts named Gog and Magog. The first sections of this structure were believed to havebeenbuilt during the Spring and Autumn Period. The rebel Li Zicheng was defeated by a combined force of Manchus and General Wu Sangui's [[SAHNG-GWEES]] loyalists at this structure's namesake fortress in the Battle of Shanhai Pass. For ten points, name this series of fortifications across northern China. ANSWER:Great Wallof China (accept WanliChangcheng) 2021-22 C Set History (9) A series of works titled Anti-[this collection] were written by political figures including John Dewitt and George Clinton. Both \"checks and balances\" and \"separation of powers\" are advocated for in the 51st piece of this collection, which also states the legislative branch is the true voice of the people. The name\"Publius\"wasusedbyMadison, Hamilton, and Jay to write, for ten points, what collection of essays supporting the ratification of the U.S. Constitution? ANSWER:TheFederalistPapers(orTheFederalist;the full title isTheFederalist: A Collection of Essays, Written in Favour of the New Constitution, as Agreed upon by the Federal Convention, September 17, 1787) (10) In Islam, this book isidentifiedwithapre-IslamicholybooktitledZabur.Portionsof this book labelled mizmor were originally intended to be sung. Many sections of this book are attributedtoAsaphandtheSonsofKorah.The23rdchapterofthisbookbeginswiththe line \"The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.\" For ten points, name this Old Testament book that contains many poems attributed to King David.",
      "answer": [
        "Book ofPsalmsor ThePsalter",
        "acceptTehillim 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The architects of this federal building were Cass Gilbert and Cass Gilbert Jr., and it was designated aNationalHistoricalLandmarkin1987.Priortoitscompletionin1935,this building's main inhabitants worked in the Old Senate Chambers. Recent workers in this building include Elena Kagan, Neil Gorsuch, and Chief Justice John Roberts. For ten points, name this building in Washington D.C., home to the federal judicial branch.",
        "answer": "United StatesSupreme CourtBuilding accepttheMarble Palace"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This politician is the only person to have served both as U.S. president and Chief Justice and was the main proponent ofbuildingthenewSupremeCourtBuildingduringthe 1920s.",
        "answer": "William HowardTaft"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler met up with Maximilian I to defeat the French at the Battle of the Spurs, though he later took part in a peaceful celebration with Francis I attheFieldoftheClothof Gold. After supporting the Acts of Supremacy,thismonarchpresidedoverthedissolutionof his country's monasteries. That occurred after this man broke from the Catholic Church in order to divorce Catherine of Aragon. For ten points, name this Tudor king of England, remembered for his six wives. ANSWER:Henry VIII[[the eighth]] BONUS: This woman became Henry's second wife after he secured his divorce from Catherine. This woman was the mother of future Queen Elizabeth I.",
        "answer": "AnneBoleyn 3 The extinct great auk lived around the northern part of this ocean, and the Grand Banks in this ocean were a major center for cod fishing until their depletion in the 1990s. The navigator Himilco might have discovered this sea's Sargasso region in the 5th century BC. Mostlikelynamedforacertainglobe-carryingTitan,fortenpoints,whatisthisoceanon which one finds the cities of Boston and New York? ANSWER:AtlanticOcean"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Grand Banks lie off the coast of this island which was possibly known as \"Vinland\" to Leif Ericson. It is the site of the Viking village L'Anse aux Meadows [[lahn-soh-meh-DOH]]. ANSWER:Newfoundland(do not accept \"Newfoundlandand Labrador\") 2021-22 C Set History (4) The Ratha was a variant of this military technology introduced during India's Harappan [[hah-RAH-pun]] period. In an effort to counter heavy hoplite [[HOP-lite]] infantry, Xerxes I [[ZERK-seez \"the first\"]] deployedthe\"scythed\"varietyofthistechnology. The Battle of Kadesh was the largest battle deploying this military technology. For ten points, name this swift, often multi-horsed conveyance used in Bronze Age warfare.",
        "answer": [
          "WarChariots",
          "descriptive answers BONUS: The Scythian tribes are believed to have used chariots during their migratory periods. They occupied what vast ecoregion of Central Asia, a largely treeless grassland? ANSWER: EurasianSteppe",
          "GreatSteppeor TheSteppes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This island's Sette Giugno [[seh-TAY JYOON-yoh]] holiday commemorates a British massacre of Italian irredentists. It's not Rhodes, but King George VI [[the sixth]] awarded this entire island the George Cross after it resisted Axis bombing campaigns. The image of Ottoman invincibility was shattered after the KnightsHospitallersuccessfullydefendedthis islandin1565.JeanParisotdeValette[[pah-ree-SOHduh-vah-LET]]namesthecapitalof,for ten points, what small island nation to the south of Sicily?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic ofMaltaor Repubblika ta'Malta",
          "acceptMelita BONUS:TheMaltaSummitbetweenGeorgeH.W.BushandthisfinalSovietleaderoccurreda few weeks after the fall of the Berlin Wall, declaring an end to the Cold War. ANSWER: MikhailGorbachevor Mikhail SergeyevichGorbachev 6 During a 1781 raid, a force commanded by this man spared the main house at Berkeley Plantation, which he planned to appropriate for his own residence. This man arrived with relief troops to break the siege of Fort Stanwix and joined with Ethan Allento capture Fort Ticonderoga.ThismajorgenerallaterworkedwithJohnAndréinanattemptto surrender West Point. For ten points, name this Continental Army officer who defected to the British in 1780. ANSWER: BenedictArnold"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the residents who escaped Berkeley Plantation through secret tunnels as Arnold approached was this then seven-year-old, who later became the shortest-serving president in U.S. history, dying shortly after giving the longest inauguration speech ever read. ANSWER:William HenryHarrison(prompt on \"Harrison\") 2021-22 C Set History (7) A New York Times editorial from the 1870s decried this activityalongsidelynchings as \"Incurable Evils.\" This activity's \"Father,\" Walter Camp, met with President Theodore Roosevelt inasummittolimitcollegiatefatalitiesinit.TheVinceLombardi-coachedPackers defeated the Chiefs in this sport's first championship following theAFL-NFLmerger.Gerald Ford played the \"Center\" position for the Michigan Wolverines in, for ten points, what American sport?",
        "answer": [
          "AmericanFootball",
          "GridironFootball",
          "acceptGridironorPigskin BONUS: Immediately after the firing of Hue Jackson, the Cleveland Browns made overtures suggesting they would attempt to hire this female Secretary of State under the George W. Bush administration as their head coach. ANSWER: Condoleezza \"Condie\"Rice"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Haymarket Square Riot",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Haymarket Square Riot, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Twice-elected U.S. president who was in office during the unrest.",
          "answer": "GroverClevelandor Stephen GroverCleveland"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Thirty Years' War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Thirty Years' War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "16th century treaty which allowed Imperial princes to choose what Christian faith to follow.",
          "answer": "Peace ofAugsburgacceptCuius regio, eiusreligio"
        },
        {
          "question": "French cardinal and \"prime minister\" who was the architect of France's entry into the war on the Protestant side.",
          "answer": "CardinalRichelieu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic League general who sacked the city of Magdeburg and won the Battle of White Mountain in Bohemia.",
          "answer": [
            "JohannTserclaes, Count ofTilly",
            "either 2021-22 C Set History"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician signed the Mulford Act, against which the Black Panthers protested by marching on his capitol bearing arms. This man called in the National Guard to quell the People's Park Protest in the city of (20 pts)",
        "Berkeley. After impressing hisfellowRepublicanswithaspeechinsupportofBarryGoldwater,thismandefeated Pat Brown to become the governor of California. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name thismanwho gave the \"Time for Choosing\" speech and was later elected presidentoftheUnitedStatesin 1980 and 1984."
      ],
      "answer": "RonaldReaganor Ronald WilsonReagan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Shapley-Curtis debate centered on whether or not this structure was a \"spiral nebula.\" The center of this structure contains a radio source discovered in 1931 by Karl Jansky, the supermassive black hole Sagittarius (20 pts)",
        "A-star, and this structure was believed by the Babylonians to be the severed tail of a dragoness. Orbited by Large and Small Clouds named for (10 pts)",
        "Ferdinand Magellan, for ten points, what is this galaxy which is home to the Sun and Earth? ANSWER:Milky Waygalaxy (3) Thiscitywasfoundedin1565byPedroMenéndezdeAvilés[[ah-vee-LEHS]]on the feast day of the patron of brewers.HenryFlaglerbuiltarailroadthroughthiscity, which was annexed into the U.S. along with the rest of its stateintheAdams-Onís(+) Treaty. This city was intended to be turned into a winter resort by an industrialist who constructed the Hotel Alcazar and Hotel Ponce de Leon. (*) For ten points, name this Florida city, the oldest continuously-inhabited European settlement in the United States. ANSWER:St. Augustine(orSan Agustín) (4) With his lover, this crown prince planned to flee to England and potentially usurpthethronefromhisfatherduringtheKatte[[KAH-tuh]]Affair.Thefailureofthe Austrians and Russians to follow-up on the Battleof(+)Kunesdorfwasknownasthis king's \"Miracle of the House of Brandenburg.\" This German's victory in the Seven Years' War led tohiscountry'sannexationof(*)Silesia.Fortenpoints,namethis\"Great\" king of Prussia during the mid-18th century. ANSWER:Frederickthe Great (orFriedrichder Große[[\"GROSS\"-uh]]; acceptFrederick II; orFriedrichII; acceptOld Fritz; or DerAlteFritz) 2021-22 C Set History (5) The Bandeirantes [[bahn-deh-RAHN-tehs]] were adventurers in this modern nation who dressed like Jesuitstodupenativesintoenslavement.Thoseraidersoften spoke Língua Geral [[LEEN-gwah heh-RAHL], a (+) pidgin which mixed this country's European language with Tupi. This South American nation allied with Argentina and Uruguay in a \"Triple Alliance\" to halt Paraguayan aggression. Pedro (*) Cabral discovered, for the point, what large former Portuguese colony?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Federative Republic ofBrazilor RepúblicaFederativa doBrasil",
        "Kingdom ofBrazil",
        "or Reino doBrasil"
      ]
    }
  ]
}